MANAS NAIDU BANDARU





Data Analyst

OBJECTIVE: Conscientious data analyst professional with extensive 5+ years of experience utilizing SQL and machine learning knowledge to develop technological solutions that help with business turnarounds as a part of a dedicated team of data analysts. Multifaceted roles have touched on several core business disciplines from sales and marketing to customer services



Education

University of Cincinnati University - Ohio, USA

• Computer Science / Masters

Technical Skills

- Business tools: Rational Requisite Pro, Doors, UML 1.4.MS
 Visio MS Office, MS Excel, MS Power point
- ETL and Data Integrations: Informatica PowCen, Alteryx
- Cloud Platforms: AWS, Azure, GCP, Snowflake.
- Methodologies: Agile, Waterfall, Rational Unified Process RUP, Software Development life Cycle SDLC, Gap Analysis, Use Cases. Workflow diagrams
- Languages: Python, R, SQL, C#, PL/SQL, Java
- Web Technologies: JavaScript, HTML, and CSS
- Databases: MS Access 2000/97/95/3.1, MS-SQL Server 2000, Oracle 8i/9i, SAS database, DB2 SPSS, SQL, Oracle, DB2, Teradata, Big Data, NoSQL, MySQL, Azure Data Factory (ADF), Azure Data Explorer (ADE), Power bi
- Data Analysis/Visulization: Tableau, Power BI, Looker, DOMO, Qlik

Profile Summary

- 5+ years of Industry experience as a Data Analyst with Master Data Management MDM solid experience in Information Technology with expertise in data warehouse design, development, implementation and maintenance.
- Worked extensively with Microsoft Excel Macros, VLOOKUPS, and Pivot Tables Proficient Microsoft Word Power Point
 Access and Lotus Notes, Skilled in acquiring, cleaning, and processing data from various sources, including APIs,
 databases, and external datasets.
- Knowledge in the ETL Extract Transform and Load of data into a data warehouse/data mart and Business Intelligence BI
 tools like Business Objects Modules Reporter, Supervisor Designer, and Web Intelligence
- Efficient in elicitation techniques like interviewing, questionnaires, brainstorming, focus groups and cost benefit analysis.
- Having experience in data modelling tools such as Informatica Data Explorer IDE and data quality tools such as Informatica
 Data Quality IDQ
- Proficiency in SQL (both DDL & DML queries), adept at using SQL to define, manipulate, and query data stored in relational
 databases, Extensive experience working as backend tester by writing SQL Queries and PL/SQL scripts on large data
 warehouse systems involving Terabytes worth of data
- Strong hands-on ability to use SQL in RDBMS SQL Server, Oracle for verifying source data preparation and assisting of data design input and troubleshooting, Strong knowledge of Business Intelligence, Data Warehousing and Business Architecture, Designed and implemented stored procedures views and triggers for automating tasks in TSQL
- Combined **Google Looker** with other **technical skills** (Created data models **in Look ML**, enabling **dynamic** dashboard updates with **SQL**-based data **pipelines**).
- Extensive **experience** in **Strategic** development of a **Data Warehouse** and in Performing **Data Analysis** and **Data Mapping** from an operational **Data Store** to an **Enterprise Data Warehouse**
- Conducted JAD sessions with CRMs SME, system Architectures, Technical teams and other stakeholders for open and pending issues, expert in developing and implementing web-based applications with C and MS Visual Studio .NET.
- Extensively worked on Dimensional modelling, Data cleansing and Data Staging of operational sources using ETL processes, Extensive Data Warehousing experience using Informatica as ETL tool on various data bases like Oracle, SQL Server, Tera Data, MS Access.
- Experience integrating ADF with other Azure services (Azure Databricks, Azure Functions, Logic Apps, etc.) for complex data workflows experience in building Power BI reports on Azure Analysis services for better performance.

- Knowledge of software Development life cycle SDLC and a thorough understanding of its phases like Requirements.
- Analysis/ Design Development and Testing In depth knowledge of RUP's Iterative Software Development Life Cycle process i.e. Inception Elaboration, Construction and transition.
- Proficient in Technical and Business Writing Business Process Flow, Business Process Modelling Business Analysis and
 Testing various complex data driven methodologies for commercial lines integration with Documentation
- Extensive experience with the SAS programming and in data step and with various SAS Procedures in Base SAS and SAS/Stat, including thorough knowledge of SAS Macro.
- Expertise in Project Management i.e. Project Scoping, Planning, Estimating Scheduling, Organizing, Directing,
 Controlling, Budgeting and Drafting Remedy Procedures

Work Experience

Client: Asurion, Nashville, Tennessee, USA

November 2023 - Present

Role: Sr. Data Analyst

Description: Asurion, LLC is a privately held company. It provides insurance for smartphones, tablets, consumer electronics, appliances, satellite receivers and jewellery. I gather and compile the data from various internal and external sources.

Responsibilities:

- Responsible for providing data analysis that is focused on improving user experience and optimizing user retention.
- Wrote complex ad-hoc MySQL queries involving correlated subqueries, window functions and common table expressions to
 track user activity metrics such as retention rate and daily active users. Optimized existing queries to run faster on larger datasets.
- Designed and maintained MySQL databases, and created pipelines using user-defined functions and stored procedures for daily reporting tasks.
- Developed dashboards in **Tableau** and presented data to track **KPIs** and product performance using data from various sources such as **MS Excel, AWS S3, AWS RDS, AWS Redshift, JSON** and **XML**.
- Spotted and analysed trends in user activity data, identify underperformed user segmentations and reported insights to stakeholders.
- Designed metrics for **A/B testing**, creating dashboards in **Tableau** to monitor test processes, analyse test results, interpret and give recommendations to stakeholders.
- Performed statistical analysis such as hypothesis testing, causal inference and Bayesian analysis.
- Communicated between the business, product managers and data engineers to ensure the data quality.
- Built ETL pipelines to retrieve data from NoSQL databases and load aggregated data into the analytical platform.
- Managed data storing and processing using big data tools such as Hadoop, HDFS, Hive and Spark.
- Developed **Python scripts** to automate data validation and data cleaning processes such as deduplicating and checking data consistency using **Pandas** and **Apache Airflow**.
- Analyzed large scale user log data and generated features for classification models using SparkSQL in Spark.
- Implemented scalable machine learning models **Random Forest** using **SparkML** and **Python** to predict **customer churn**.
- Applied advanced classification models such as XGboost, SVM and Neural Networks to train data using Python packages such as Scikit-learn.
- Defined metrics to estimate impact of new features and give recommendations for business decisions based on data analysis.
- Created dynamic dashboards and reports using **Tableau**, **Power BI**, **Looker**, or **Qlik** to communicate insights visually.
- Build data visualizations (charts, graphs, heatmaps) using **Python libraries** (Matplotlib, Seaborn) or **R packages** (ggplot2, Plotly).
- Orchestrated end-to-end data pipelines using Apache Airflow, integrating diverse data sources including NoSQL databases, AWS services (S3, RDS, Redshift), and big data technologies (Hadoop, HDFS, Hive, Spark) to ensure efficient data flow and processing for analytics and reporting purposes
- Ensure data privacy, integrity, and security, adhering to protocols like GDPR or HIPAA.
- Implement and follow data governance standards for managing sensitive or confidential data.
- Participated in data project planning, gathering business requirements and translating them into technology requirements.

Environment: Tableau, KPIs, MS Excel, AWS S₃, AWS RDS, AWS Redshift, JSON, XML, ETL pipelines, Python scripts, Pandas, Apache Airflow, SparkSQL, Hadoop, HDFS, Hive, Spark.

Client: Community Health Systems, Franklin, Tennessee, USA December 2022 - October 2023

Role: Sr. Data Analyst

Description: Community Health Systems (CHS) is a publicly-owned hospital operator and one of the largest healthcare delivery systems. Maintained and updated the databases, ensuring data accuracy and integrity.

Responsibilities:

- Expertly translated business requirements into robust data models, optimizing resource utilization for maximum efficiency.
- Leveraged advanced **DAX query** techniques to create dynamic computed columns in **Power BI**, enhancing data analysis capabilities.
- Created Row level security with **power BI** and integration with **power BI service portal**.
- Designed and developed highly interactive reports featuring dynamic column selection, intuitive conditional formatting, customizable sorting, and flexible grouping options.
- Extensively used **SSIS** transformations such as **Lookup**, Derived column, Data conversion, Aggregate, Conditional split, **SQL** task, **Script** task and Send mail task etc.
- Worked on all types of transformations that are available in **Power BI Query editor**.
- Published Power BI Reports in the required originations and Made Power BI Dashboards available for Web clients and mobile apps, Power Apps
- Used **Power BI, Power Pivot** to develop data analysis prototype, and used **Power View** and **Power Map** to visualize reports.
- Use SQL or other query languages to extract data from relational databases (MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQL Server).
- Retrieve and aggregate data from various sources (APIs, cloud databases like AWS, Google BigQuery, or Snowflake) for analysis.
- Implement data pipelines using tools like Python or ETL tools (Alteryx, Apache NiFi).
- Translate data into actionable insights that help business teams make informed decisions.
- Monitor and report key performance indicators (KPIs) using BI tools to track business performance and forecast trends.
- Apply predictive modelling techniques such as **linear regression**, **decision trees**, or **clustering algorithms** using **Python** (Scikit-learn) or **R** for forecasting and trend analysis.
- Work with machine learning models for predictive analytics, customer segmentation, and optimization tasks.
- Manage data in cloud data warehouses like AWS Redshift, Google BigQuery, or Snowflake for efficient data storage and processing.
- Use **SQL** for querying and managing data within data lakes or data warehouses.
- Used Dataflows, Power Automate features to work efficiently for further dashboards
- Involved in creating new stored procedures and optimizing existing queries and stored procedures.

Environment: DAX Queries, Power BI, AWS Redshift, Google Bigquery, Kusto Query Language (KQL), Dataflows, dashboards, SQL, Lookup, SSIS

Client: Kotak Life Insurance, Hyderabad, India May 2021 - July 2022

Role: Data Analyst

Description: Kotak Life Insurance (Kotak Mahindra Life Insurance Company Ltd.) is a well-established private life insurance company in India, part of the Kotak Mahindra Group. I designed and implemented interactive dashboards and reports using Google Looker and Power BI to visualize policy sales, customer engagement, and claim performance,

Responsibilities:

- Created Source to target data mapping documents identifying key data elements and prepared Data Flow Diagrams
- Created/Reviewed data flow diagram to illustrate where data originates and how data flows within the Enterprise Data warehouse EDW, Responsible for delivery of all customers' shareholder and employee dash board metrics as per goals.
- Supported data warehouse projects with logical and physical data modeling in Oracle environment and assured accurate delivery of DDL to the development teams Structure and organize data models in Power BI.
- Performed extensive data modelling to differentiate between the OLTP and Data Warehouse data models
- Facilitated sessions with the senior management to identify business flows and determine whether any current or proposed systems are in compliance with HIPAA guidelines.
- Worked extensively on Azure data factory including data transformations Integration Runtimes, Azure Key Vaults Triggers
 and migrating data factory pipelines to higher environments using ARM Templates

- Worked with the development team to ensure that they understand the functional specifications.
- Implemented **Master Data Management MOM** for all entities in the **project** by maintaining a **master** hub for improving the data quality by following various **data governance** techniques and **data dictionary** standards.
- Executed SQL queries using TOAD for Oracle dB and AQT for DB2, for data extraction and validation, developed application using Visual Basic Wrote reports using Crystal Reports and MS Access.
- Assisted in monitoring ancillary data transactions and addressed problems with HL7 messages.
- Involved in the formulation of Business Requirements Document BRO after all business requirements were defined clearly, Creating Dash Board using visual Basic and integrating with business objects
- Writing **VBA** macros to automate repetitive tasks in **Excel**, such as data entry, **formatting**, and report generation.
- Extensive use of **Excel** to create **Functional** Specification **Documents** Templates
- Writing functional and technical specifications, creating source to target mapping, designing data profiling and data
 validation jobs in Data Stage and creating ETL jobs in Data Stage, Manage the vendor selection process via a formal RFP
 process, Involved in Testing by using SQL and work with QA together to develop test Scenarios and test cases.
- Analyzed Business Requirements and segregated them into high level and low level Use Cases, Activity Diagrams I State
 Chart Diagrams using Rational Rose according to UML methodology thus defining the Data Process Models.

Environment: data mapping, Data Flow Diagrams, HIPAA guidelines, SQL queries, TOAD, Oracle dB, Azure Key Vaults, Excel, VBA, pipelines, Chart Diagrams.

Client: Reliance Jio, Hyderabad, India

Mar 2019 - April 2021

Role: Programmer Analyst

Description: Reliance Jio, a subsidiary of Reliance Industries Limited, is India's largest telecom operator, offering a range of digital services including mobile connectivity, broadband, and digital platforms, I developed custom scripts and tools to streamline operations and reporting, reducing manual workload for the technical and marketing teams.

Responsibilities:

- Integrated third-party APIs and payment gateways to improve e-commerce functionality, increasing checkout efficiency
- Automated deployment pipelines using CI/CD tools, reducing release cycles by 30% and improving the reliability of software updates, assist other project teams with data analysis data mining and data profiling as needed.
- **Developed custom scripts** and tools to streamline operations and **reporting**, reducing manual workload for the technical and marketing teams,
- Involved in **mentoring** specific projects in **application** of the new **SDLC** based on the **Agile Unified Process**, especially from the **project** management **requirements** and **architecture** perspectives.
- **Developed SQL-based** data warehouse environments and **created multiple** custom **database** applications for **data archiving**, analysis and **reporting purposes**.
- **Prepared UAT Materials UAT** Test Cases to include **various** steps involved for **UAT** and to have **proper** coverage of requirements, **extensively** used **ETL** to **load data** from **Oracle database**, **SQL Server Flat files**
- Performed Data mapping, logical data modeling, created class diagrams and ER diagrams and used SQL queries to filter
 data, Implemented Excel pivot tables for extraction of informative data from these databases using SAS excel plug-ins.
- Experience in data governance/ data stewardship business/systems analyst needed to work as part of a team on data governance and writing SQL queries
- Worked on Performance, Tuning and loading data for fast access of reports in Client Database Server balancing, business
 Rules Implementation Meta Data, Data Profiling.

Environment: APIs, CI/CD tools, scripts, SDLC, SQL-based, UAT Materials, ETL, Oracle database, SQL Server Flat files, SQL queries, pivot tables, SAS excel